Finding Aid for Promote Michigan Committee Records 1983-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Promote Michigan Committee Records 1983-1984
Promote Michigan Committee
0.4 linear ft.
Organization formed in opposition to the Voter's Choice Amendment, an amendment to the state constitution to roll back taxes to their 1980-1981 level. Scattered minutes, agendas, mailings, and collected material relating to the Committee's political activities.
861064 Bj 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The records were received from the committee in December 1984. Donor no. 7145
The collection is open for research.
The Promote Michigan Committee was formed June 5, 1984 as a broad based coalition of groups to fight Proposal C, an amendment to Michigan's constitution designed to roll taxes back to 1980-1981 levels. By the time Proposal C came up on the November, 1984 ballot, the Promote Michigan Committee had garnered support from industry, organized labor, social service agencies, educators, and many other groups. The committee was able to raise funds and volunteers more readily after the executive committee approved the hiring of a staff and renting of an office in late August. Two co-directors, Jim Briney and Ray Brennan, focused the campaign and mapped out strategies. The Promote Michigan Committee effectively blanketed the state with a sustained media blitz which was effective in persuading voters to defeat Proposal C. Promote Michigan officially dissolved on November 15, 1984.
The Promote Michigan Committee collection provides some insight into how a professionally organized, well-funded, broadly based campaign successfully opposed tax reduction. The records are arranged alphabetically by type of material. The agendas, minutes, and correspondence provide some sense of the day-to-day functioning of the committee, but they are neither detailed nor complete. The background materials and press releases discuss the issues involved in tax reduction and amply delineate various groups' arguments against Proposal C.
Of special interest is Ray Brennan's review of the Committee's actions, "Keep our Comeback Alive." This is a report on the campaign's context, strategy, literature, finances., and results, and it is helpful in capturing the essence of the 1984 campaign. To gain the broader historical perspective on efforts to combat tax reduction in Michigan, one should also consult the League of Women Voters records and the Charlotte Capp collection.
Subjects:
Elections--Michigan--1984.; Michigan--Politics and government--1981-1990.; Michigan--Politics and government--1951-; Promote Michigan Committee; Social action--Michigan--Societies, etc.; Taxation--Michigan.
- Election files
  - Historical Review, "Keep our Comeback Alive," 1984 (Box 1)
  - Analysis of Proposal C's Economic Impact, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Agendas and Minutes, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Background Research and Reports, 1984 (Box 1)
  - General, 1984 (Box 1)
  - State of Michigan, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Correspondence and Memos, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Legal (petition drive and Jim DeMar brief), 1984 (Box 1)
  - Press Releases, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Resolutions of Other Groups on Proposal C, 1984 (Box 1)
  - "Voter's Choice" Materials, 1984 (Box 1)
    (includes audiocassette of speech of Dick Chrysler in favor of Voter's Choice)